this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
PC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
[Music]
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle I'm excited
to invite yens neusa as our guest on the
show today for a conversation about back
ends for front ends
Jens is the founder of Wonder graph a
Next Generation BFF framework designed
to optimize front-end full stack and
back-end developer workflows through API
composition
he is also the creator of graphql go
tools a golang based open source project
to build graphql middleware proxies and
API gateways used by many graphql API
vendors in the industry as well as many
Enterprises
Jens welcome to the show hi Jeff thanks
for having me absolutely
in a recent conversation you and I had
you mentioned that a lot of front-end
development teams bear the burden of
integrating with lots of distinct apis
and it seems like there's always new
dependencies that they're taking on so
from a high level from your perspective
what can be done to reduce this
integration and coupling burden so yeah
I think on a high level perspective what
we currently see over the last couple of
years is we decompose larger systems
into smaller parts we use more and more
SAS systems that provide individual apis
to solve a very specific problem
and what we're actually trying to figure
out is what is the right place to
integrate all those systems into one
unified API interface
and obviously there's different places
where we can handle this integration and
I would say from our front-end
developer's perspective it can be a huge
pain if you have to do all of that with
almost no tools that help you facilitate
that do it in the front end there's
security pitfalls but also most
front-end Frameworks if you look at what
they are actually good at in terms of
you know binding data to the user
interface and facilitating that but what
do front-end Frameworks have to offer
for this modern development use case
where you want to integrate with
multiple services and most of the time
there's really barely anything so you're
looking for new ways to solve that
problem and I think that's a it's a huge
challenge for front end but also full
stack developers so it sounds like
you're saying that the front-end
Frameworks while they may be useful
they're not not necessarily helping
solve the challenge of how do I
integrate with a bunch of different apis
as a front-end developer yeah exactly
and I actually think this is also a good
thing because not necessarily is it the
right place to solve that sort of
problem and I think the UI Frameworks
like react next.js views velter I think
the way they are scoped is really great
and usually what you find is that you
have this one front end and it talks to
this one API that's your backend and
that works very very well however as we
said earlier in the discussion we see
that we have more and more services and
Integrations we want to build with and
then we have payments and stripe and
other sales services for sending sms and
and whatnot and we have so many
different systems we're now using I
think for example at at wunderguff we
have at least 40 different vendors that
we use ourselves that provide something
to us if you want to integrate all of
that in the front end or wherever you
actually want to integrate that it's a
challenge by itself yeah what's maybe
one of the worst things you've seen from
a front-end integration standpoint we
just mentioned 40 vendors so if you have
40 vendors now their own apis I mean
have you seen situations where front end
teams are literally bearing the burden
of trying to integrate tens or dozens of
different apis together in the front end
well I think one of the obvious problems
you can very easily see and then that it
simply shows the struggle of especially
younger front-end developers is when
people go to stack Overflow and ask
where do I put my environment variables
into my react application
and you see from the way how they phrase
that question it's kind of obvious that
yeah obviously they like you should
never put a secret of sort or an API key
into your react application and I think
there's a kind of like a gap in
education and we need to talk more about
you know composable architecture and
different roles and responsibilities
like what kind of Logics should sit in
the back end what kind of logic should
sit in the front end and for me
personally worst case you have a front
end that talks to many different systems
with different protocols all the
Integrations happens in the front end
you got huge waterfall requests when you
visit a new page requests depend on
requests depend on more requests you
have like lists and then nested fetches
it all goes to different services and at
the end of the day for me what's the
biggest nightmare about this kind of
architecture you actually don't really
understand what this application depends
on and it's very very unclear if
something is slow or doesn't properly
render or you're unhappy with the scores
your website gets in like Lighthouse
which is a performance check for
websites you don't really know what's
the cause and it's just very hard to
track that down
so when teams begin some of them with
integrating everything in the client
what do they often do as a Next Step
maybe they're feeling this pain they're
realizing that oh it's really hard to do
retry and roll back logic in the front
end it's really hard to make sense of
all this complexity of you know
Integrations with all these different
things so what's often a Next Step that
those teams start taking and then talk
to us a little bit about the challenges
of maybe what their next attempts tend
to be
yeah so as you have more and more modern
front-end Frameworks that also support
server-side rendering for example
next.js has this API directory and what
you can see is that a lot of people
simply start writing or adding the API
integration layer into that API route
directory and so they are moving this
logic from the client to the server it
is still in the same repository and it's
kind of like the same level of
complexity what's a bit better is we now
have a security boundary between client
and server and we are potentially closer
to the apis that we're integrating with
so we can eliminate some latency but if
you look at the core problems that we
need to solve you will see that a
framework like next.js and others are no
different
there are super agnostic in terms of
helping you with API integration like
you can create an API endpoint kind of
like a rest API thing and that's what
you get from the framework and the rest
is on you and you need to ask yourself
the question we have so many apis a lot
of them public like GitHub and Shopify
and stripe and others should every
developer should every application that
integrates with them should everybody
write more or less the same kind of
logic to integrate apis
and we had a very interesting discussion
earlier today because we did a live
stream with the founder of SST backstrap
we were talking about this topic what's
the difference between building an
application and building a library and
what we came up with or what our
conclusion was is when you're building a
library like two libraries on different
problems like SST and wondergov they are
probably completely different because
they're solving so different problems
but when you compare a couple of
e-commerce apps or just next.js
applications they will actually share a
lot of codes and that's kind of
especially in the integration part does
it actually make sense that we write so
much manual integration code yeah so
teams might start moving to the back end
but to your point while they may gain
some benefits of a security barrier and
maybe they can reduce some latency
they're essentially just moving the
complexity to another place and it
sounds like from your perspective
something is trying to emerge here and I
think one of the next steps you've
mentioned the teams start to go to is
they start realizing that whether they
like it or not they're kind of now
building their own back end for their
front end so maybe lean into that a
little bit especially for listeners who
aren't familiar with what is back end
for front end you know where does the
term come from and then let's talk about
some of the pitfalls when teams discover
that they're actually starting to build
their own BFF framework yeah I think it
was 2012 I really hope I don't get it
wrong but it was around the time where
SoundCloud came up with the term backend
for front end and it's essentially the
idea that you have or back then you have
one single monolithic API or it could
actually be also microservice
architecture so it's agnostic in that
room but let's say you have a bunch of
services and then you don't have one
particular fronted but multiple and and
back in 2012 I think it was this trend
to go towards mobile so what you usually
had is you had like I would say your
main API surface and then you had a
backend for front-end for the website a
backend for front end for your IOS app
and the back end for front end for your
Android app simply because the
requirements of each individual app and
the website were so different that
SoundCloud thought wouldn't it make
sense if we have a specific back end for
each individual front end so it's kind
of like a I know you could say maybe a
shim but it's actually I think it's a
bit more than just that so it's kind of
like a layer on top of your API layer
that simplifies cross-cutting concerns
like authentication and API composition
and other patterns pulls that into the
BFF and then you don't have to handle
that in the front-end code
right and it sounds like they're two if
I understand you correctly that they
were building sort of platform-specific
back-ends for certain kinds of front
ends so maybe here's the mobile one that
has slightly different API surface area
than maybe the web yeah sort of bringing
the integration barrier down a little
bit for teams that were maybe on a
specific type of footprint for a device
yeah exactly like if you think about app
development more specifically you're
probably aware that once you change an
app it needs to go through the App Store
review at least on IOS and Android I
think it's a bit more automated and you
usually have to support a native app for
a very long time because not every user
will update that so that means if you
have a web application that is very fast
paced like you know you can redeploy the
web app the front end and the BFF and
the moment they change they can change
together so you can continuously change
your BFF and how the website talk talks
to that for an IOS and Android app you
cannot continuously change them because
you need to maintain those old versions
and and you know one of the core
paradigms in software development is you
want to keep things together that change
together and you want to keep things
separate that's change separately so you
have a different release cycle for iOS a
different cycle for Android and a
different cycle for your web app and
also the requirements of each individual
app are different so I think it's kind
of makes a lot of sense that you figure
out these boundaries and for each of
those you have a BFF and that can handle
versioning it can maintain old API
versions and that also gives you that's
another interesting pattern here it
gives you a facade pattern where you can
actually put a facade into your BFF that
can sit or that can sit between the
internal API and an old version of the
Android app and you can keep maintaining
that facade you can change internal
systems but as long as you keep the
facade up to date and maintain that old
applications will keep running and
that's one of the big benefits here of
using such a BFF
yeah it's interesting too because a lot
of what you're describing there in the
more abstract is about layering and in
his book a philosophy of software design
John osterhout talks about deep modules
and I'll put a link in the show notes to
the appearance that he had on this show
but I think that's what a lot of people
end up discovering is if we just had
these very flat systems where it's
essentially a database with an HTTP shim
on top of it with a front-end react
application then there's a ton of
coupling to your data models you're
gonna have you're going to have a ton of
problems with how do you you know handle
transactions and complexity especially
as you adopt other apis and systems but
broadly speaking there seems to be this
growing recognition of a need for more
deep deep layering and of course layers
have a cost they can introduce some
latency they can introduce complexity
but it seems like we're finding cases
where this layering is actually quite
warranted and makes some things far
simpler than the alternative yeah I
actually think that sometimes we're very
enthusiastic about optimizing something
down from 100 milliseconds to 95
milliseconds but at the same time we're
wasting a whole month or two of precious
engineering time and what's the actual
user benefit at the end of the day so
yeah yeah I agree performance is a
feature but if you're eking out three or
four percent you know that's different
than if you can eke out you know 10x or
100x in performance now I'm listening
now maybe it's worth that additional
engineering effort
so one of the things you said to me in a
previous conversation which I thought
was an interesting concept was that you
recommend that apis be treated as
dependencies like any other package so
talk a little bit about what that means
and what the benefits are of taking that
approach
yeah so you know when we write code
let's say we created next JSF and we
decide we want to use some sort of
dependency servers or an SDK or we just
want to add some code to our application
the way we do that is we npm install a
package and then we have something it is
called the package manager we have a
package Json file and with the
package.json file we have a list of our
dependencies for code and we know
exactly okay we installed this package
it is now in node modules and we know
what our application depends on in terms
of code
now we're building a BFF with our next
JS stack so what do we do we add axios
or install an SDK
and with axios we make some fetch calls
to an API where is the package Json
where do we actually know what we depend
on and why is not everybody
shouting from the roof that something is
wrong like we have such a great pattern
you know we have go modules we have
crates in Rust we have Maven in Java
land we have npm and for apis we have
kind of implicit dependency management
and that for me as I was building this
solution and started talking about API
dependency measurement I felt like it is
so obvious to do that right
yeah it makes sense to me I mean you
know we've all heard of the two hard
problems left in computer science right
cache and validation naming things and
off by One problems but you know I
typically say there's two hard problems
left in software engineering information
hiding and dependency management and
what you're highlighting here is
dependency management is more than just
about package management it's also about
when you integrate with an API of some
kind you are also taking on implicit
dependencies and boy I heard the phrase
I don't remember the source of it but
you know let's make the implicit
explicit and I think that's exactly what
you're calling out here which I think is
great I mean if you look at larger
companies or even smaller ones our
startup with 40 different vendors if you
look at or Genuine question for you if
you look at a recent company you work
with and you looked at one of their
backends and you glanced at the code of
their back end did you have an idea of
what this back end depends on in terms
of apis was it obvious
in terms of apis no in terms of code
modules as you said absolutely it's
pretty straightforward but as far as
what apis it depends on it's very opaque
yeah and for me I think it's a huge
problem because we simply we have all
this code but we actually don't
understand what's happening it's so
intransparent and yeah I'm very
enthusiastic in actually making that
more transparent and explicit in saying
hey we have this BFF because we're
building a BFF for our mobile app and
this BFF it depends on these five
microservices and one SAS service for
sending sms and now it's it's very
obvious and we can tell everybody in the
company this is what we depend on this
is our quality of service we have this
one operation it's actually slow because
of that one microservice and we can
trace all of that and I don't know life
would be a better place yeah and you
know now if you have that you can
imagine that things like observability
and Telemetry become simpler tracing as
you mentioned because now you have a
clear sense of how these different
actual dependencies are affecting your
system as opposed to just treating code
modules as dependencies and forgetting
that apis are dependencies
so I imagine there's some challenges to
this approach like for example you know
I know a lot of people use things like
open API and Swagger and you know maybe
there's some skeptical listeners who are
saying that's enough that's sufficient
so maybe explain a little bit about
where that kind of an approach isn't
sufficient to solve these kinds of
problems we're talking about
yeah I think the biggest challenge with
API dependency management and automating
the process of building BFFs is actually
that every API is kind of different it's
actually a huge problem to find
open API specified apis that have like
the same level of quality so usually
open API can due to the nature of open
API is used to document existing apis
not always to go like API definition
first and then implementation so your
varying levels of quality and then
obviously you don't just have rest apis
so in my previous jobs we had grpc soap
weird XML apis custom HTTP apis so if
you want to implement API dependency
management you actually need to find
some sort of common denominator to
facilitate that right and unfortunately
it seems like the common denominator
typically is I don't even call them rest
apis because you know if you read Roy
fielding's thesis which we'll put a link
to in the show notes rest is extremely
uncommon true rest but setting those
debates aside not every API is an HTTP
API right as you mentioned this grpc
this graphql there's even things like
async API where you know you start to
look at I mean the real word that
matters an API for my perspective is
interface well an interface is just a
contract about you know data can flow
between these two things and this is
what the messages look like and that
could have lots of different protocols
and transports and things like that so
that definitely I think is one of the
challenges and when we reduce to the
lowest common denominator we often end
up trying to push Square pegs into round
holes well I totally agree yeah well you
kind of talked a little bit about it but
let's dive into some of the patterns
that are involved when adopting a back
ends for front ends approach and you let
me know before the show that you've
actually set up a new website BFF Dash
patterns.com so I definitely encourage
listeners to check that out but let's
talk a little bit about some of these
patterns and maybe give our listeners a
flavor for what they can expect in their
world if they're trying to build back
ends for front ends for their systems
and simplify the front end Integrations
for their client delivery teams yeah so
first off API adapter let's maybe talk a
little bit about that first one and say
what is an API adapter and how does that
relate to the back ends for front ends
approach yeah so API adapter is really I
would say one of the like together with
API composition it's kind of like one of
the simpler models where you have let's
say a composed schema of API so you
combine a bunch of apis into what you
could call if we want to stay generic
let's just say that's a composed graph
that represents the multiple apis and
then we have an adapter on top of that
for different flavors of our web
application so in this sense we have a
mobile app that uses three services then
we have a web app that uses some other
three services and we have a third-party
API that depends on two other services
and in this case the adapter is simply a
subset of the whole composition of apis
we have okay so then let's talk a little
bit about API composition and maybe we
can see how these two patterns tend to
relate yeah API composition I would kind
of say it is very much related to API
adapter in the sense that API
composition allows you to say okay we
have five different apis and they can be
rest graphical or maybe even a database
or something that doesn't by itself
speak HTTP and API composition allows us
to say that we combine all of them into
one single unified API and expose that
to our applications and what that
essentially allows us to do is a client
doesn't have to depend on multiple
Individual Services but it can rather
depend on this facade which is the
composition of our services so it
doesn't have to understand the different
protocols and and languages and
interfaces it simply has one single
interface it can talk to okay so putting
these two things together now just to
kind of paint a picture for our
listeners from the composition
standpoint I'm saying maybe I have to
talk to three or four different apis
these could be graphql these could be
rest these could be databases some
combination of those and step one and
composition is let's collect all those
together into a singular like API like a
super API but then the adapter side of
it is let's not ship all of the super
API out to our clients let's give them
adapters that are catered to the
specific needs of mobile or web or
whatever footprint they may be dealing
with yes so for example let's say you
introspect a database and you create an
API schema from that and you add the
rest API and the graphical API you can't
imagine how big the API surface actually
now is so do you want to explain suppose
that whole API surface that even exposes
internals of your database do you want
to expose that all the way to the client
probably not so you might want to have
an adapter that sits on top of that that
creates just another API layer which for
example could be a rest API or Json RPC
and that's now the communication layer
between the deployed application and
your BFF which also means that you can
leverage this layer to enforce loose
coupling because the API composition can
change but the facade or BFF it can keep
the contract between client and BFF
intact right and here's where you can
get your information hiding and you can
improve your dependency management
because now your front end is not
directly coupled to your super API but
the super API is giving you the power to
support these adapters and facades that
meet the specific needs of the specific
front-end applications so you kind of
it's sort of like you're trying to
balance the details between meet the
needs of the front end but also meet the
needs of the integrator so the
integrator is not having this complex
mess of wires you just kind of integrate
it all together by composing it together
into a I don't know if super API is the
right term but yeah you know for example
there's a couple of tools and over time
they are a bit more popular and then a
bit less but there's a couple of tools
that generate you an API from a database
and some people love to connect this
directly to the front end yep and that
makes you extremely fast for the first
couple of days and it makes you super
efficient and sometime later the
application is deployed someone comes up
with a brilliant idea which is very
regular to change the name of the
database table and because the API is
derived from the names of the table you
just broke your API you just broke your
client so it's always Traders like
something that makes you like you you
need to be suspicious when something
makes you extremely fast because maybe
that's a trade-off you're currently
making yeah I mean you know I could
strap a you know a rocket engine to my
back and I might be really fast but that
may not be very safe or sustainable yeah
well let's talk a little bit about API
coordination that's the next pattern
from the BFF pattern site what's the
problem here with API coordination that
we're trying to solve yeah so one use
case that we keep coming back to is as
much as I love rest apis sometimes rest
apis are very granular and they want to
cater different use cases so they are
not specifically designed for a given
user interface which is good they are
designed around a resource like a
shopping cart or something and then what
can happen is and this is what some of
our users keep running into I need to
make 17 rest API calls to populate the
data I need for this View
and API composition you're laughing I
know I should be crying okay yeah so big
content developers they didn't have a
better way of doing that and the fastest
way of integration it was really just
front-end they didn't know better with
the API coordination pattern what we do
is we create an endpoint on our BFF and
that allows us to talk to multiple
services do the 17 API requests or
whatever we need combine it all together
and then send it back to our clients so
our client makes one single request our
BFF handles all the coordination and
that makes the whole thing a lot easier
for us in the client side so essentially
if you're trying to coordinate calls to
two different Services instead of having
the front-end developer try to
coordinate that call and then of course
handle errors and retry and this sort of
a thing this is pushing that
coordination logic back into your BFF so
that the front end's not responsible for
that coordination logic exactly yeah I
see this all the time that's why I was
laughing I mean if if you don't put
workflow into your backend system it
will emerge in your front-end system and
it will be painful yeah that's why I was
laughing but like by the way brings me
to the point you need to invite I'm not
sure if he was here yet but you should
maybe invite the founder of xstate okay
stately okay it's very interesting
because you can talk with him about
State machines you just reminded me of
like you have state machines everywhere
and and a lot of the time State machines
are like it's a different problem space
but a lot of the time we have state
machines we make them implicit as well
yes or they show up as if else logic
which is also a kiss of death for
complexity yeah so next pattern is API
evolution
how does this pattern help us in a BFF
world so I think that's actually one of
the most important patterns and it's
also because we want to change things
and it's also like kind of correlated to
what we said before with the database
that we directly exposed to our front
end
if we use the API Evolution pattern if
we have a BFF that sits between client
and actual backend we can have an
endpoint that represents some logic we
can have that on our BFF and it
essentially wraps some Legacy API and
over time we can slowly change the
implementation without breaking the
client and that's that's essentially how
we can slowly move off like an old
service or something and if you have not
just web apps but also like mobile apps
stuff like that you will always want to
keep an old contract up and running and
so in in this case you can use the API
Evolution pattern great I think that's
actually one of the problems like you
mentioned before the ability to spin up
a database rapidly ship you know quote
API I'm doing that in scare quotes and
now you've basically directly coupled
your phone into your database and what
API evolution is so solving for is the
dynamic nature of the systems that we
build meaning they're going to change
but how can we accommodate that change
over time instead of creating brittle
and fragile systems where every time
something changes we have to redo
everything yeah that's exactly a point
next pattern is API lens this one might
be a little bit challenging to present
since we don't have the visuals that we
can show but talk a little bit about API
lens and how maybe it's similar but
different to the API adapter pattern
yeah I think API lens in a nutshell is
we have let's say we have our supergraph
of API dependencies that's our composed
API graph from that we create an adapter
but we realize we have actually like two
different variations of how we want to
use that adapter so we can have even one
more layer on top of that like an API
lens that gives us like one more option
to to filter out something else a use
case here could be you compose your apis
you create that adapter which is your
your layer on top and now a third-party
vendor comes around the corner and says
hey I want to integrate with you and you
don't want to give them the whole
adapter because that might have some
internal things so you put a lens on top
of that that really just gives them
exactly what they need and then that
filters out everything else I see and so
from the adapter it looks like it's more
about adapting for a specific kind of
client like a device or a web versus
with the lens it's it's kind of an
adapter as well it's a way to organize a
set of endpoints and apis together but
it's doing it for a different reason it
might be as you said you want to expose
things to another you know third-party
imagine another use case might be that
you maybe want to organize things by
something more related to the business
domain and so you want to be able to
create a lens that that's oriented
around you know these all relate to a
certain kind of user for example so
we're going to consolidate these
together so similar to the adapter but
kind of with a different purpose I guess
okay
and then how about API name spacing yeah
so that's something very early on when I
started experimenting with the idea of
treating apis like dependencies what I
realized is that we don't just need to
steal the dependency management pattern
from code we also need to steal the
namespacing pattern because it's kind of
obvious that if you combine
two or more apis especially like like
from public renders or even if you just
combine two two databases it's very easy
to have naming conflicts like everybody
has a user nobody cares like when you
create a database you you don't
namespace your types because you you
don't think of that or these names being
used in another context so what we
actually need to do is when we combine
multiple apis and treat them like
dependencies we need to figure out a way
to name space things so that you don't
have a user in stripe and a user in
Salesforce and then it's kind of big use
what is what and should the should the
fields of the two users merge or what do
we actually do like they are not the
same thing so at the end of the day what
the solution here is that you have a
stripe user and you have a Salesforce
user and that way you can you can very
easily identify them distinguish and
that's also what you have in let's say
typescript for example you import the
module and you can Alias that and that
way you you avoid the naming conflicts
and that's that's essentially what we
also need for apis if we apply API
dependency measure yeah that makes sense
too that the more apis you start
integrating with the more risk of
collisions you're going to run into so
having these kinds of patterns in the
early stages may seem like well why
would I need that I'm only talking to
one API but as you extend and expand and
you start talking to more you're going
to start running into these situations
where you're going to need some of these
these techniques to help you avoid
collisions and and things of that nature
yeah cool now we've gone through the
patterns of backends for front ends
let's talk through a couple of the use
cases for backends for front end so the
first one you mention is API
consolidation so talk a little bit about
what API consolidation is and what
problems it helps us solve
yeah so this is actually where I more or
less started my career in this space I
was working for Germany's largest News
website to online we were building
essentially a BFF out of the requirement
that and we we did that in a manual way
back then so if you if you think about a
news website we had a Content management
system we had data providers that gave a
like football data financial data Sports
rather than we had Integrations with
Amazon affiliate we had our own internal
systems that spoke like graphql we had
something we had rest apis all sorts of
things and so
this whole use case it's about
combining apis composing them together
into a single unified interface and make
it simpler for a developer to develop
against a heterogeneous set of systems
and that really sounds like what a lot
of people are trying to get to but
they're doing it either through pain
driven development right by trying to
integrate in the client or as you said
they're ending up building their own
backends for front ends you know
approaches but it sounds like and we'll
get more into this later in the show but
it sounds like there's some patterns
emerging for maybe how to do this in
more consistent ways as we're trying to
simplify Our Lives of our of our client
developers yeah another use case you
mentioned is the universal SDK which I
get really excited when I see Universal
SDK but I'm going to let you explain
what it is and why it relates to
backends for front ends yeah so when we
started working on the back end for
front-end space the first step for us
was to build this API consolidation
layer where we translate different
protocols and and different API
specifications into the common
denominator and then have the user or
allow the user to speak one single
language against all these services and
what we realized is at some point that
you cannot just so in in our case I want
to make it a bit more specific so we
allow our users to talk graphql to all
their API dependencies and that was our
starting point graphql in this sense is
great because it has one feature that no
other API style has because it's a query
API style you have one component end of
the graphical spec which is the
selection set and with the selection set
you can select as the name suggests a
subset of the API surface and that is
essential for API integration because if
you combine and compose multiple apis
and you might even Nest them you need to
have a way of cutting off the tree of
data because you you don't want like to
eat out you don't want to query
everything you want to limit what you
have and obviously you could do
something like that with rest apis as
well there are specifications as far as
field sets for example and other ways to
Define I want to have a subset of a
resource but I think graphql is is just
better in in doing that because it has
such a native feature we have the
specification but regarding the
universal SDK what we realized after a
while is our our users
they are not happy with the pure
graphical approach because sometimes you
want to get some data from a service and
you might want to join it with another
data source but you want to massage the
data a bit you want to map it or you
simply want to create a facade that is
not derived from the back end so from
your API dependencies but you really
want to have a decoupled facade that is
defined by itself so the facade defines
okay here's an operation has an input it
has response shape and then you can
Implement that so we we learn from our
users building BFFs that Simply Having
something like a graphql API Gateway it
is not enough to implement a BFF they
sometimes want to have some custom logic
and so we allow them to write custom
logic with typescript and from
typescript
we also allowed them to call into
predefined operations against the
graphql schema that we have generated
and that caused a little bit of friction
because
whenever you wanted to create a custom
operation that also uses graphql to talk
to your API composition what you had to
do is first you define a graphical
operation then you wait a little bit for
the code generation process that creates
some some type so everything is typesafe
and then you can use that from your
operation definition and that calls a
little bit of friction because it it was
just a little bit slow and and yeah we
weren't happy with that so we had a new
idea what if we take the API composition
so the the whole graph of all our apis
which is essentially a graphql schema
what if we take that
and generate from it in SDK
so that in our case you can simply use
typescript and talk to all your API
dependencies in kind of like an orm
fashion what this allows you to do is
from a workflow perspective
step one you add your API dependencies
to your BFF
Step 2 you create an operation in
typescript step 3 you use the universal
orm and you talk to all your
API dependencies as if they were just a
database and you had an or on top of
that and that it makes the whole process
of integrating and combining apis it
makes it so smooth you don't have to
think about okay is this soap is this
rest is this grpc no it's really just
you have an S Universe SDK you just call
into the services you need you massage
the data you pass it back BFF done okay
and you're using the language that
you're used to and you're using
constructs that are common to your
language you're not having to sort of
Paradigm Shift like that's one of the
things that orms are meant to do as well
right is I'm not so much worried about
SQL if I need to I can go under the hood
and I can get there which anyone who has
experience with orms know you often have
to do but most of the time I'm a layer
of abstraction removed and it just
simplifies my interactions so in a
similar way I don't need all the Gory
details of HTTP configurations and grpc
configuration or whatever I can just say
I'm dealing with objects I'm dealing
with classes and types yeah and final
use case is uh API upscaling yeah I
think we slightly talked about this
before but it's kind of like related to
the Legacy pattern where you have your
facade your BFF yeah you have that BFF
depending on some Legacy API and then
over time you replace that with newer
Services that's for example something
that I I actually see a lot when people
decompose monolithic systems into
smaller composable parts you put a BFF
in front of the monolith that keeps the
contract intact and then you you start
strangling the monolith slowly and and
Outsourcing some of its functionality
into another service reconnecting that
through the BFF and with that keeping
the the facade between your BFF and the
client intact right so in this case
you'd be using API coordination but not
necessarily for some kind of a business
workflow you'd be doing it to keep your
legacy system and your new system in
sync until the time that you could
finally shut off the Legacy system and
migrate everything everything over to
your new new approach exactly yeah which
is great because we see these headlines
like you know large Fan Company ditches
microservices it goes back to the
monolith and of course if you dig into
the details you realize that there's
more to the story than that and and what
I think we're really struggling with as
an industry is finding what's the right
level of granularity like you know too
many things with too many
interconnections is not good and too few
things with too few interconnections is
not good what's the right answer well
it's somewhere in the middle but it
seems like that's often what we're what
we're grasping for here in tools like
this would give the ability to
experiment even with kind of how you
factor the granularity of some of these
things but you can Shield your front-end
teams from worrying about the details of
that which seems really powerful yeah
you know often when I hear these stories
I I feel like we should actually talk
more about how to properly structure
monoliths because I usually feel like
you can get very very far with a
well-structured monolith but the problem
is if you are not good at software
architecture and you're unhappy with
your monolith why do you think it's
going to be better with the distributed
system
like yeah I don't now you're adding
Network boundaries and and all sorts of
complexity and and I don't want to say
that I'm against microservices not at
all it's just I just recently had a
conversation with with someone who was
talking about they were using Apollo
Federation which is a graphql framework
to building microservices and I asked
them about their team size and they said
they are a team of one and they had two
applications and so I don't know but as
a startup as a small startup we have 13
Engineers we have one single monolith
because we really cannot afford like
first of all we all work together we're
still one team and we just cannot afford
the coordination and overhead of
maintaining multiple services like we we
just have one very boring back end and
that's you know the you build exciting
stuff with borrowing components
well you said something before in the
show I believe you referred to
composable architecture and that's the
right answer it's not microservices
versus monoliths it's how do we build
things that are composable and if you're
doing that then you can be somewhere on
a spectrum of those things but you know
I appreciate what you're saying too
about how your team affects these things
and yes it's ironic that a single
developer team is you know managing a
full you know Apollo Federation or you
know maybe managing multiple kubernetes
clusters with like one developer and
it's like maybe you would have been
better off with a monolith and try to
find your product Market fit without a
bunch of additional unnecessary
complexity but hey I don't know your
context so but definitely something to
think about I want had one thing because
you mentioned composable architecture
there's this recent trend of new
startups that do authentication in some
way or the other
and what I usually do is I I look them
up I go to their docs and I type into
the Search openid connect
because I'm building an API integration
product and what is amazing about
composability and specifications open
specifications like openid connect is if
you build a new product because our our
service integrates with open ID connect
obviously we delegate authentication and
yeah you build a new product you just
implement the open ID connect spec and
you can immediately work with so many
other systems and services and it's it's
just amazing and so many of them
don't Implement openid connect but build
some fancy UI and and stuff I don't know
I I think that's the wrong direction
yeah to me it would be like if I'm
building the cool new Appliance for your
home but it requires a special
electrical outlet and you have to call
an electrician and put in a new panel
and put in right and like here's the
special plug but this Appliance is so
awesome it's like wouldn't you rather
just your Appliance plugin to standard
full electrical plugs wouldn't that be
better for your business but again we
don't know your business but it's again
definitely good good food for thought
good analogy in the time we have left
talk a little bit you mentioned Apollo
Federation as a contrast but maybe dig a
little a little bit more into for us
what is Wonder graph specifically do to
help support teams that want to build
back into front ends and how is it maybe
differentiated from some of the other
vendors and options that are out there
yeah so I I don't want to say we
invented the idea of API dependency
management uh it's not important who
invented that I guess probably some
other people have talked about that
before but we've built a framework to
really facilitate creating BFFs super
simple and and to give you like a
well-rounded package where you can say
Okay I want to build a front end for
that I want to have a BFF I can add my
API dependencies to my BFF that can be
rest soap grpc anything databases in the
future we want to support async API as
well because I think that's really
exciting use case combining different
messaging patterns sync and async and
then essentially the the workflows I
described it a bit earlier you create
your BFF you add API dependencies and
you can then Define operations against
your API dependencies and from that we
generate for one the BFF API service and
second we generate whatever front-end
framework you want to integrate that
with like view clients well to whatever
and that it really streamlines
everything from building full stack
applique locations we integrate with S3
for example for file storage so that's
just you know the mentality what you
just said with the standardized plug in
Wonder graph you can say in the in the
front-end code that we generate you can
use the same API to upload a file and in
the backhand side you can configure the
S3 storage and that can be whatever you
have like AWS or digital ocean spaces or
menu
and we do the same pattern with
authentication you plug whatever you
have there but the client-side API is
login and so yeah we really try to
abstract away common patterns that we
see in the in the BFF space so that not
every developer has to reinvent the
wheel and I think one of the most
exciting benefits of this approach and
going that route is that you can make
the API dependencies of your systems
explicit and something that we're going
to do in the future is that we want to
help companies map in real time what
depends on what and what uses what
service and what is super interesting
about this use case is we talked about
API Evolution earlier
one of the huge burdens of evolution and
and companies especially bigger size to
move fast is you have some application
that depends on 10 different Services
the 10 different Services they want to
change because it's not Hardware it's
software so you want to improve or
change those Services if you don't know
who depends on your services and you
don't know how they are using your API
how can you ship a change with
confidence and so what we want to bring
to companies is first of all we map out
what depends on what we have all these
facades so we know exactly okay here's
the front end it depends on this and
that and then we give
back-end developers or individual teams
the tools to extrapolate if you make a
certain change to your API and we can
run that in continuous integration if
you make a certain change it will affect
the following Services what should we do
should we above that operation should we
add an extra middleware to keep that
compatibility or how should we treat
that and so what we really want to do is
embrace
apis as dependencies and give developers
the tools to move fast to change things
but not to break things
yeah and that's great and from those
patterns we looked at earlier in the
show even as you're describing that I'm
thinking I have now I have options as a
developer you know I'm making an API
adapter an apad lens or is this an API
coordination we're going to support two
or or you know am I going to do you know
the more like the API Evolution details
like we talked about so if I have some
tools and patterns that I can follow
then I can say here's the pros and cons
of these different approaches to solving
this problem instead of you know what
ends up often happening is well here
I've got bailing wire and duct tape
let's just throw something together and
cross our fingers and hope it works so I
like the empowerment piece there being
able to say these are the tools in my
Arsenal that I can use to solve these
complex problems when things change and
let's be honest requirements change all
the time so if we try to Design Systems
you know that are coupled to
requirements it's it's no wonder we
constantly have pain yeah so what do you
envision is the future of apis where
would you like to select a lot of what
you're describing here it sounds like
this this glorious future where you've
manager dependencies and we know how
things interrelate and we can do impact
analysis on on when things are going to
change so where would you like to see
the industry go as far as the future of
apis is concerned so the way we see
ourselves currently is
we are in the kind of pre-docker era in
terms of containers if we translate that
to apis so there was a an error where we
didn't have Docker we didn't have
containers and we were just manually
installing software dependencies and
trying to run that on different
platforms that's how I see the API
landscape today and what we're now
building or what we have built is I
would say this first step the
dockerization of apis so we've built our
our open source framework to enable API
composition and to enable this whole
workflow of apis as dependencies and the
next logical step for us and that's how
I see the future is that we build a
platform to enable real collaboration
between API producers and API consumers
because what I see today is that the
company like stripe uploads an open API
specification to GitHub and that's not
really how I see collaboration the way I
see collaboration is that we have have a
platform where people in the open source
Community they can contribute apis we
can see what depends on what how are
apis being used public and private we
can see how apis evolve our time we can
discuss and propose changes we can do
all sorts of collaborative things and
most importantly we can Empower
developers to continuously change apis
and services without breaking each other
and I would really love to see a future
where something happens like you know
you have an API specification it's
published on what I call the GitHub for
apis it's published on on that someone
opens an issue asks for a change because
they have a suggestion how to improve
that API at some point later there's
some sort of pull request mechanism or
something this new feature is being
added once that is closed there's a
notification that gets published
everybody who's consuming that apis get
notified hey here's a new feature change
lock blah blah and then everybody else
who's using that API through a
standardized BFF all they do is pull an
update on their API dependency they now
have this new feature they can use for
example the universal SDK integrate that
and the whole workflow is done and now
the API provider gets the immediate
feedback through analytics because the
BFFs the facades and the API provider
they can coordinate and exchange data so
the API provider would get immediate
feedback that people are now using this
new capability they exposed and I think
that would would just be an amazing
future of API collaboration yeah I
really like that vision of being able to
understand my dependencies understand
the impact of potential changes and
actual changes and then being able to
have patterns that I can pull off the
shelf for accommodating those changes as
well and the just the consistency and
the clarity that that could help provide
the industry seems like a really bright
future so it's awesome to see that
yourself and and people like you are
working on helping us to solve those
kinds of complex problems so if people
want to find out more about what you're
up to where should they go so we have
wondergraph.com this is our main website
you can learn more about what we do
there in general then obviously on
GitHub so everything we build is open
source you can go to github.com wonder
graph there you find a couple of Open
Source repositories and then if you want
to follow me on Twitter from time to
time I tweet something it is Jensen's
noise underscore d e great and also one
of my listeners again about BFF
patterns.com which is also another
resource where you can find out more
about back-ends for front ends well Jens
thank you so much for joining me today
on software engineering radio thanks for
having me this is Jeff Doolittle for
software engineering radio thanks so
much for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]